<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council Res. No. 049-13">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective/>
    <history>
      <adopted/>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council Res. No. 049-13</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Stockbridge-Munsee Community, Band of Mohican Indians, is a federally recognized Indian tribe with inherent sovereign powers, and is governed by the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council pursuant to the 1937 Constitution;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Stockbridge-Munsee Community has the authority under its Constitution and its inherent rights as a sovereign nation to adopt and amend	Ordinances;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Tribe has adopted a Worker Compensation Ordinance, Chapter 52, to provide tribal workers with compensation and medical care when they are injured on the job; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Tribe wishes to adopt amendments to that ordinance to cover law enforcement officers who respond in mutual aid to a request by the Tribe and to update the process for appointing an administrative law judge; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>the Stockbridge-Munsee  hereby adopts the following amendments to Chapter 52, which include the following changes:</text>
      <text>
        <ul proof="needed">
          <li>Creating a new Subsection 52.2 (L)(4); and</li>
          <li>Amending Section 52.11 (B)(1-3).</li>
        </ul>
      </text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council, hereby certify that the Council is composed of 7 members, of whom ____, constituting a quorum, were present at a meeting duly called, noticed, and held on the ____ day of _______, 2013, that the foregoing resolution was duly adopted at such meeting by a vote of ____ for, ____against, and ____abstaining.</text>
    <text>_______________________					________________________</text>
    <text>Robert Chicks, President					, Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
