<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code">
  <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
  <num>21</num>
  <heading>FISH AND WILDLIFE ORDINANCE</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>PART</prefix>
    <num>I</num>
    <heading>GENERAL PROVISIONS AND ORGANIZATION</heading>
    <section>
      <num>21.1</num>
      <heading>Tribal Council Purpose and Findings</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Council finds that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>One of the most important short and long-term resources is the fish and wildlife of the Stockbridge-Munsee Community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The fish and wildlife are important cultural resources to the Tribe.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The Tribe desires to manage the fish and wildlife for present needs and for future generations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Certain species need protection in order to survive as a species.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Properly managed natural resources will provide an excellent environment for natural habitat such as fish, wildlife, natural herbs, wild flowers, and forest resources.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>The Tribe's ownership of fee land, forest crop fee land, managed forest fee land, and the United States' ownership of federal trust and proclaimed lands for the benefit of the Tribe implicates Tribal, federal, and state law depending on the ownership of the land.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>The Tribe's increasing land base, home building, economic development, and reforestation efforts necessitate increasing involvement and management of the natural resources by the Conservation/Ecology Departments, the Fish and Wildlife Board and the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>All enrolled members of the Tribe shall have a right to share in the beneficial use of the natural resources of the Tribe's trust and fee lands.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(I)</num>
        <text>All individuals with privileges under this ordinance also have a responsibility to be good stewards of the natural resources on the Tribe's trust and fee lands.  While tribal members do have a right to share in the bounty from the land, they must do so in a responsible manner that ensures the long-term continuation of healthy and sustainable natural resource populations for the benefit of future generations.  This responsibility extends to maintaining a healthy environment for sustaining those fish and wildlife resources as all life is inter-connected.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.2</num>
      <heading>Authority</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Ordinance is authorized under Article VII (f) of the Stockbridge-Munsee Constitution, and its inherent powers, as an exercise of its governmental powers to govern the use, management and administration of lands, waters, fish and wildlife of the Stockbridge-Munsee Indian Reservation.  Such authority is essential to protect the political integrity, economy, and the general welfare of the Stockbridge-Munsee Community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>In addition, the Stockbridge-Munsee Community has authority over tribal lands owned in fee simple by virtue of its ownership of such land and its authority over the conduct of its members and may enforce this Ordinance consistent with such authority.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.3</num>
      <heading>Definitions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>"Big game" shall mean, but not be limited to deer and bear.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>"Fish and Wildlife Board" means the body appointed by the Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>"Conservation/Ecology Departments" means the departments and entities such as the game warden(s) and the ecologist (s).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>"Fur-bearing animals" shall mean beaver, mink, muskrat, otter, skunk, raccoon, fox, weasel, opossum, badger, coyote, fisher and bobcat.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>"Infraction(s)" means violations of this Ordinance as further identified hereunder, including in Sections <cite path="§21.17">21.17</cite>, <cite path="§21.21">21.21</cite>, <cite path="§21.24">21.24</cite>, <cite path="§21.26">21.26</cite>, and <cite path="§21.28">21.28</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>"Migratory birds" shall have the meaning set forth pursuant to the Migratory Bird Treaty Act, 50 CFR Part 10.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>"Minor" means a person under the age of 18 years old, at the beginning of the season for which they hold a permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>"Pan fish" means, perch, bluegill, crappie, sunfish, and rock bass.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(I)</num>
        <text>"Permittee" means a person who is a direct descendant, a spouse of a Stockbridge-Munsee tribal member, or a legally-adopted minor child of an enrolled Stockbridge-Munsee tribal member.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(J)</num>
        <text>"Small game" shall mean all wild animals not defined as big game, turkey or fur bearing animals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(K)</num>
        <text>"Special Permit" means a ceremonial harvest permit issued by the Tribal Council for the harvest of fish or game for use at a feast or other ceremonial occasion; a disabled permit issued by the Tribal Council to accommodate a tribal member's physical disabilities.  Such permits are issued upon such terms and conditions as the Tribal Council deems appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(L)</num>
        <text>"Spring Hole" means the area of the West Branch of the Red River, commonly known as the Spring Hole.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(M)</num>
        <text>"Tribal Court" means the Stockbridge-Munsee Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(N)</num>
        <text>"Tribal Council" means that the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Tribal Council.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(O)</num>
        <text>"Tribe" means the Stockbridge-Munsee Community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(P)</num>
        <text>"CITES" is an abbreviation for Convention on International Trade in Endangered Species.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(Q)</num>
        <text>"Bow" is a general term for a weapon that fires arrows and includes recurve, compound, longbow, and crossbow.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(R)</num>
        <text>"Adult Bear" is a bear that measures 42 inches or greater in length, as measured in a straight line from the tip of nose to the base of tail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(S)</num>
        <text>"Cub" is a bear that is less than 42 inches in length, as measured in a straight line from the tip of the nose to the base of the tail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(T)</num>
        <text>"Public Road" refers to any road that is intended to provide a route for public access, such as roads listed on the Indian Reservation Roads inventory or other local road inventories, as well as driveways to facilities that are open to the public.  In addition, the railroad bed from Morgan to Camp One Road is treated as Public Road for the purpose of this Ordinance, however, this treatment does not grant any access rights to the general public.  Forest roads, as defined in Chapter 22, are not Public Roads.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.4</num>
      <heading>Jurisdiction</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>This Ordinance shall apply to all lands and waters of the Stockbridge-Munsee Reservation, which for purposes of enforcement of this Ordinance includes proclaimed reservation lands and tribal trust lands as well as individual trust lands under the jurisdiction of the Stockbridge-Munsee Community.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>This Ordinance shall also apply in relation to lands that the Tribe owns in fee simple; however, such lands may be subject to state laws or may be subject to terms of an agreement between the Tribe and the State of Wisconsin.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.5</num>
      <heading>Fish and Wildlife Board</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>General Powers.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>In addition to the powers of the Fish and Wildlife Board bylaws, the Fish and Wildlife Board is authorized to oversee conservation policy on the Stockbridge-Munsee Indian Reservation in accordance with this Ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The Fish and Wildlife Board may develop and recommend to the Tribal Council other conservation rules and regulations that shall not violate the provisions of the Tribal Constitution, this Ordinance, or any other tribal law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The Fish and Wildlife Board may exercise those powers authorized under this Ordinance, and as directed by the Tribal Council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The Fish and Wildlife Board will follow all applicable Tribal law including Chapter 51, Code of Conduct.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Duties and Responsibilities of the Board.  The Fish and Wildlife Board shall:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Meet on a regular basis and submit their meeting minutes to Tribal Council.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Make recommendations to Tribal Council regarding amendments to this Ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Make recommendations to the Tribal Council regarding conservation resource policy issues.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Make recommendations regarding Special Permits.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Request assistance from the Conversation/Ecology Departments to fulfill the Fish and Wildlife Board's responsibilities, as needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.6</num>
      <heading>Conservation/Ecology Departments</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Conservation/Ecology Departments, departments of the Tribe, are responsible for carrying out the functions and policies of the Tribe relating to the natural resources, which are consistent with this Ordinance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Conservation Department shall have authority to enforce the provisions of this Ordinance utilizing Authorized Law Enforcement, the Tribal Prosecutor, and the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Court.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The Conservation/Ecology Departments shall work with the Fish and Wildlife Board, the Environmental Department, and other departments to ensure that water quality, fish stocks and fish spawning areas are not harmed by activities controlled, regulated, or authorized by the Conservation/Ecology Departments.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Nothing in this Ordinance is intended to limit the Conservation or Ecology Department's ordinary functions, duties, or responsibilities.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.7</num>
      <heading>Tribal Council</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council has overall authority to approve recommendations from the Conservation/Ecology Departments and/or Fish and Wildlife Board regarding conservation issues, policies and procedures.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council may temporarily alter seasons, limits, fees, permit requirements, close areas, or waive provisions of this ordinance, if the Tribal Council determines that it is in the best interests of the Tribe and that an emergency exists, other similar circumstances exist, or there is not adequate time to amend this Ordinance.  The Tribal Council must also determine that if it does not act, the Tribe or its conservation resources will be harmed.  Any actions under this provision must be acted on by Resolution, and in accordance with Chapter 50.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council may also issue any Special Permit upon such terms and conditions the Tribal Council shall deem appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The Tribal Council may also waive any provision of this Ordinance for special cultural or ceremonial events such as the Chemon Welch fishing derby, or other similar events.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>This section is not intended to be any limitation on Tribal Council's inherent or constitutional authority.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>No one is authorized to release non-native animals or plant non-native plants on tribal lands without Tribal Council approval.  This does not apply to individual gardens on land assignments or authorized community gardens.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>PART</prefix>
    <num>II</num>
    <heading>HUNTING – BIG GAME (DEER, BEAR), TURKEY, SMALL GAME AND MIGRATORY BIRDS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>21.8</num>
      <heading>License, Permits, and Harvest Tags (Enrolled Member and Minor-Aged Direct Descendent)</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Enrolled members of the Stockbridge-Munsee Community shall not be required to purchase or possess hunting permits when hunting, possessing, or transporting any game lawfully taken within the boundaries of the Stockbridge-Munsee Indian Reservation, provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>the enrolled tribal member has his or her valid tribal identification card in his or her possession; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>when hunting, the enrolled tribal member is at least 12 years of age and has successfully completed an approved hunter safety course and possesses a certificate for such course EXCEPT that enrolled tribal members who are at least 10 years of age and less than 12 years of age may also hunt subject to the criteria outlined in <cite path="§21.8|(C)">Section 21.8 (C)</cite> herein; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>all hunters must have harvest tags in their possession while hunting big game and turkey.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Permittees who are minor-aged direct descendants may receive a permit to hunt deer on the Reservation during the tribal season; provided:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>the permittee is at least 12 years of age and has successfully completed an approved hunter safety course and possesses a certificate for such course, EXCEPT that permittees who are at least 10 years of age and less than 12 years of age may also hunt subject to the criteria outlined in <cite path="§21.8|(C)">Section 21.8 (C)</cite> herein; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>if under 16 years of age, the minor must be accompanied by an adult tribal member while hunting.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Enrolled tribal members and permittees who are at least 10 years of age and less than 12 years of age may hunt on the tribal land so long as:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>they have successfully completed an approved hunter safety course and possess a certificate for such course; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>there is only one (1) weapon that is jointly possessed between the minor and the adult; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>they are within an arm's length of an adult who is legally-authorized to hunt with that weapon during that season at all times; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>the minor and adult comply with all other hunting laws, seasons and bag limits.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>As long as an eligible person is enrolled in high school when he/she turns 18-years of age, then that person may obtain hunting permits as a minor-aged permittee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>As long as an eligible person is not yet 18-years of age at the time when a specific hunting season begins, then that person may obtain and use a hunting permit as if a minor-aged permittee for that season.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>Permittees who are minor-aged direct descendants are required to have their permit on their person or in their possession.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>Any person who hunts within the jurisdiction of this Ordinance shall have in their possessions either an enrollment card or a valid permit. The enrollment card or permit must be in possession when:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Carrying a firearm or bow,</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Shooting, trapping, taking or possessing small game or fur bearing animals.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Transporting game.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>Any person born after August 15, 1992 must have successfully completed an approved hunter safety course and possess a certificate in order to hunt on the Reservation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(I)</num>
        <text>Big game and turkey hunting requires all hunters to possess valid harvest tags as provided in <cite path="§21.18">Section 21.18</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.9</num>
      <heading>Permittee Hunting Permits and Fees</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Permittees may hunt within the Reservation provided that they have a valid Hunting Identification Permit issued by the Land and Enrollment Department and comply with all applicable law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Fees for adult direct descendants and spouses of tribal members are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Deer, migratory birds, and small game hunting permit is $30.00 annually.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A Sportsman permit for hunting and fishing, which is valid for the calendar year, is $50.00 annually.  A Sportsman permit is not valid for turkey hunting.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Turkey permit for spring or fall is $8.00.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>There are no fees for minor-aged direct descendants, however they must obtain a permit from Land &amp; Enrollment.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Permittees are required to have their permit on their person or in their possession while hunting deer, migratory birds, and small game.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Permittee hunters must have harvest tags in their possession while hunting deer and turkey.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.10</num>
      <heading>Deer Hunting Regulations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Deer hunting season is from August 15 to January 31 for tribal members and minor direct descendants.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>The taking of deer shall be limited to four (4) per person per season for tribal members (at least 2 must be antlerless), except as permitted in <cite path="§21.10|(B)|(1)">Section 21.10(B)(1)</cite>.  Minor direct descendants shall be limited to one (1) deer per season.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A tribal member may request that up to two (2) antlerless deer be donated to them from another Tribal member.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>The donee can request up to two (2) deer donation tags from Land and Enrollment Department.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The donee must inform Land and Enrollment who the donee will give the donation tags to.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Only another enrolled tribal member may fill or use a donation tag.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Deer hunting for adult direct descendants and other Permittees is limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <heading>Bow season:</heading>
          <text>September 15 through December 31.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <heading>Firearm season:</heading>
          <text>from the Saturday of the week before Thanksgiving to the Sunday following Thanksgiving.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Permittees under this section are limited to one deer per year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.11</num>
      <heading>Group Deer Hunting/Assisted Harvest</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Group Deer Hunting, also referred to as Party Hunting, is defined as at least 3 or more hunters who are hunting together within sight or voice contact of another person at all times and harvest a deer for another member of the group.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Individuals are allowed to participate in group deer hunting as follows:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>An enrolled tribal member may participate in a group deer hunt so long as at least one hunter in the group has a valid, unused carcass tag and the hunter with the tag has agreed another hunter in the group can fill that tag for him/her if a deer is harvested.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A permittee can only participate in group hunting activities during the time frame from the Saturday of the week before Thanksgiving to the Sunday following Thanksgiving so long as:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>the permittee had a valid, unused carcass tag at the start of the 9-day permittee gun deer season, and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>at least one hunter in the group has a valid, unused carcass tag and the hunter with the tag has agreed another hunter in the group can fill that tag for him/her if a deer is harvested.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Hunters may not use electronic devices (except hearing aids) to get someone to tag a deer.  It is legal to use electronic devices for reasons other than getting someone to tag the deer.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>It is illegal to kill deer for another person, EXCEPT, as part of group deer hunting activities allowed under this Section or when filling a deer donation tag under <cite path="§21.10|(B)|(1)">Section 21.10 (B)(1)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.12</num>
      <heading>Hunting Regulations – In General</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Equipment.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>No permanently anchored hunting equipment, including tree stands, cameras and targets, may be used on tribal property.  Equipment is considered to be permanently anchored when nails, screws or other similar items that can damage trees are used to anchor the equipment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Tribal members and permittees may leave hunting equipment in place over-night, so long as the equipment has an identification tag.  Tags can be acquired from the Tribe's Land and Enrollment Office.  Untagged equipment will be subject to confiscation and removal.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Baiting and Feeding.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>No person may place or use bait or feed material for the purpose of hunting any wild animal, other than bear as permitted under <cite path="§21.13|(B)|(4)">Section 21.13 (B)(4)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>No person may place or allow the placement of any material to feed wild animals for non-hunting purposes, except as allowed for birds and small mammals under <cite path="§21.12|(B)|(3)">Section 21.12 (B)(3)</cite>.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Material may be placed solely for the purpose of attracting and feeding wild birds and small mammals for non-hunting purposes, if:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Placed in bird feeding devices and structures at a sufficient height or design to prevent access by deer;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>The structures and devices are within 50 yards of a dwelling for human occupancy; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>When deer are found to be utilizing bird feeding devices or structures, the devices or structures shall be enclosed or elevated higher to prevent access by deer.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Big game may not be taken with any rim fire cartridge or with any caliber firearm of .22-caliber or less.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Arrowheads for deer hunting must be made of all steel barbless design, not less than one (1) inch wide for single two (2) blades and not less than three (3) inches in circumference for three (3) or more blades.  Arrowheads with blades of mill-tempered spring steel which contain a plastic core or ferrule conforming with the above dimensions, with a minimum weight of seventy-five (75) grain may be used.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.13</num>
      <heading>Bear Hunting Regulations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Only tribal members may take bear.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Only adult bear may be taken during bear seasons.  The season for taking bear shall be September 1 to December 1, except that the season for taking bear with aid of dogs shall be as described in subsection (C).  Individuals shall be limited to taking one (1) bear per person per season.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to molest any bear in its den.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to shoot or molest a cub or any adult bear accompanied by cub(s).</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Nothing in this Ordinance shall prohibit the taking of any bear, which poses an immediate threat to human safety, livestock or to personal property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Bait may be placed and used for the purpose of hunting bear, except that no person may place, use or hunt over bait that:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Is placed outside of the baiting season, which is April 15 to November 30;</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Has a volume of more than 10 gallons; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Is not totally enclosed in a hollow log, a buried container, a hole in the ground or a stump and that is capped with logs, rocks, or other naturally occurring and unprocessed substances to prevent deer from accessing the bait.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Standards for Hunting Bear with Aid of Dogs.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The season for hunting bear with the aid of dogs shall be September 1 to October 31.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The season for training dogs by pursuing bear shall be July 1 to August 31.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>It is illegal to hunt, pursue or train with more than a total of 6 dogs at one time regardless of the number of bear hunters in a group or the ownership of the dogs.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Dogs may be used to recover bear taken from November 1 to November 30; provided, the Conservation Department or game wardens are notified prior to the dogs being used solely for the recovery action.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.14</num>
      <heading>Turkey Hunting Regulations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Turkey hunting requires harvest tags and turkeys must be registered consistent with <cite path="§21.18">Section 21.18</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Spring Turkey Season:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The spring turkey season is open to tribal members and permittees.  Tribal members may harvest four (4) tom or jake during this season.  Permittees may harvest two (2) tom or jake during this season.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Hunting season for tribal members is March 1 to May 31.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Hunting for permittees is April 15 to May 31.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Fall Turkey Season:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Fall turkey season is open to tribal members and permittees.  Tribal members may harvest four (4) turkeys of any sex.  Permittees may harvest two (2) turkey of any sex during this season.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The fall hunting season for tribal members is from September 30 to December 31.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The fall hunting season for permittees is from October 15 to December 15.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.15</num>
      <heading>Small Game, Migratory Bird and Grouse Regulations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Small game season shall be August 1 to the last day of February.  Permittee small game season is closed during traditional 9-day gun deer season.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>There shall be a daily limit of ten (10) not to exceed twenty (20) in possession of taking of rabbit and squirrel.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Taking of Migratory Birds shall be subject to the maximum federal annual allowances provided for the Mississippi Flyway, as provided in 50 CFR Part 20.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>No lead shot may be used to take migratory birds over water.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Migratory bird season shall be September 1 to November 30.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>There shall be a daily limit of 10 ducks of any sex and any species and a daily limit of 5 geese.  The possession limit shall be double the daily bag limit.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Ruffed grouse and spruce grouse shall be limited to five (5) per day per person, and the possession and transportation of these types of small game shall be limited to no more than ten (10) grouse at any time.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.16</num>
      <heading>Commercial Hunting</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Except for the exception(s) listed herein, there shall be no commercial taking of big game, turkey or small game.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Hides of deer may be possessed and transported for commercial purposes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.17</num>
      <heading>Hunting Infractions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Class A Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any person who kills, wounds, catches, takes, traps, or has in his/her possession any bird, small game, big game, turkey, or fur bearing animal included in this Ordinance without a valid permit or permits shall be guilty of a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Taking, assisting in taking, possessing or transporting any game in violation of this Ordinance shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Wanton destruction or waste of any game animal, or bird on tribal lands shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.  Waste shall include the failure to process a game animal, or bird in a timely manner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Violating the terms and/or conditions of any Special Permit shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to use a set gun or swivel gun for any purpose.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to take game with the use of drugs, medicated bait, poison, or other deleterious substances. Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to take bear within fifty (50) yards of any garbage dump or within one hundred (100) yards of any dwelling or within one hundred (100) yards of any area designated by the Tribe as a campground.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Any person who sells, or assists, or aids in the sale of venison meat is subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>Permanent tree strands are prohibited.  Screw in steps, metal screws, or nails attached to trees are prohibited.  Violators will be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>Any person who intentionally disturbs the personal property of another person engaged in lawful activities under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Class B Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Allowing any other person to make use of his/her permit, regardless of whether or not such person would qualify to receive a permit in his/her own right, shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Exceeding established limits, using prohibited means or equipment, using bait contrary to tribal law, hunting outside of established seasons and/or hours shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Fraud in the procurement of any permit shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Any person who uses a light for wildlife viewing at night after 10 PM or who has a firearm/bow in their vehicle while using a light for wildlife viewing shall be subject to a Class B infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Class C Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Hunting while under the influence of alcohol or controlled substances shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Carrying a firearm in any motor vehicle, unless the firearm chamber is unloaded, or a loaded magazine is not attached to the firearm or the firearm is otherwise broken down, shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.  Rounds may be stored separately from the firearm or in a separate magazine, so long as the magazine is not attached to the firearm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Hunting from a snowmobile or chasing game with a snowmobile or other motor vehicle shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Except for hunting of raccoon or coyote, hunting of game animals by artificial lights shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Refusal of any person engaged in any activity relating to hunting regulated under this Ordinance to display the proper permit or identification upon request of any Authorized Law Enforcement Personnel shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to hunt with any poisoned arrow or arrow with explosive tip.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to take big game or turkey with the aid of any trap or snare, or with the aid of dogs; except bear may be taken with the aid of dogs.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to discharge any weapon across or down any Public Road, or to hunt within fifty (50) feet of any Public Road.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(9)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to deposit any game entrails, body parts, and/or hide, into the waters of any creek, stream, river or lake or to dispose of same within 150 feet of any creek, stream, river, lake, Public Road, residence or residential area.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(10)</num>
          <text>Any person who uses a vehicle or other means to block a Public Road with the intent of limiting access for other individuals to engage in activities permitted under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class C infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.18</num>
      <heading>Mandatory Registration / Wildlife Count</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>All big game and turkey harvested on the Stockbridge-Munsee Reservation must be registered.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Mandatory harvest tags will be issued to enrolled members and permittees through the Stockbridge-Munsee Land &amp; Enrollment office.  Harvest tags must be obtained by hunters each season prior to hunting.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Hunters must have harvest tags in their possession while hunting. Harvest tags must be attached immediately upon harvest.  Big game and turkey must be tagged in the following manner: Bear &amp; deer – hind leg through the gamble; turkey – around the base of the wing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>All big game and turkey must be registered with the Conservation/Ecology Departments within 48 hours of harvest and processed within 30 days of registration.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>During a State of Wisconsin closed season, big game and turkey transported off the Reservation must also receive a Wisconsin DNR transportation tag.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Before and during the applicable hunting season, the Conservation/Ecology Departments shall publish in the <u>Mohican News</u>, and tribal posting places, the applicable registration places, phone numbers, and hours.  The Tribe's web site may also be utilized.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>From time to time, but at least every other year, the Conservation/Ecology Departments will perform a count of the wildlife within the jurisdiction; particularly the bear, deer, and turkey, but also other species as needed. Data compiled is to be brought to Fish and Wildlife Board for reviews and recommendations.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>PART</prefix>
    <num>III</num>
    <heading>FISHING</heading>
    <section>
      <num>21.19</num>
      <heading>Fishing Regulations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Fees for adult direct descendants and spouses of tribal members are:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Fishing permit, which is valid for the calendar year, is $30.00 annually.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A Sportsman permit for hunting (except turkey) and fishing, which is valid for the calendar year, is $50.00 annually.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>There are no fees for minor-aged direct descendants, however, they must obtain a permit from Land &amp; Enrollment.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>There shall be no limitation on the taking of rough fish for personal use. The following regulations are imposed on the taking of: brook trout, northern pike, rainbow trout, bass (large mouth and small mouth), panfish, and walleye.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>For trout, there will be a size limit of eight (8) inches or better, and a limit of ten (10) of any kind for tribal members and five (5) trout of any kind for other permittees per day. There will be a limit for trout possession of fifty (50) for tribal members and twenty-five (25) for other permittees.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>There is a limit of three (3) bass per day.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>There is a limit of twenty-five (25) panfish per day.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>There is a limit of five (5) northern pike per day.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>There is a limit of two (2) walleye per day.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>All waters within the jurisdiction shall be closed to trout fishing from October 1 to November 30. The Spring Hole, including the creek leading to the West Branch of the Red River, shall be closed from October 1 to May 1.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The trout fishing season for tribal members is December 1 through September 30.  The trout fishing season for permittees shall be from the first Saturday in May until September 30.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Blue Heron Pond Regulations (located in NE¼ of Section 34, Bartelme):  Catch and release by tribal members and permittees is permitted.  Keeping fish is limited to tribal members and permittees age 15 and under, and 55 and older.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.20</num>
      <heading>Commercial Fishing Permits</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Commercial fishing will not be permitted.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.21</num>
      <heading>Fishing Infractions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Class A Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any person who kills, wounds, catches, takes, traps, or has in his/her possession any fish included in this Ordinance without a valid permit or permits shall be guilty of a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Taking, assisting in taking, possessing or transporting any fish in violation of this Ordinance shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Wanton destruction or waste of fish on tribal lands shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.  Waste shall include the failure to process a fish in a timely manner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Violating the terms and/or conditions of any Special Permit shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to take fish by means of explosives, drugs, poison, lime, medicated bait, or other deleterious substances. Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Any person who intentionally disturbs the personal property of another person engaged in lawful activities under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Class B Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Allowing any other person to make use of his/her permit, regardless of whether or not such person would qualify to receive a permit in his/her own right, shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Exceeding established limits, using prohibited means or equipment, using bait contrary to tribal law, hunting outside of established seasons and/or hours shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Fraud in the procurement of any permit shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Class C Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Carrying a firearm in any motor vehicle, unless the firearm chamber is unloaded, or a loaded magazine is not attached to the firearm or the firearm is otherwise broken down, shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.  Rounds may be stored separately from the firearm or in a separate magazine, so long as the magazine is not attached to the firearm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Refusal of any person engaged in any activity relating to fishing regulated under this Ordinance to display the proper permit or identification upon request of any Authorized Law Enforcement Personnel shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to use fish seines, fish traps, or gill nets, except under authority of a Special Permit issued by the Council.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Any person who uses a vehicle or other means to block a Public Road with the intent of limiting access for other individuals to engage in activities permitted under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class C infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>PART</prefix>
    <num>IV</num>
    <heading>TRAPPING</heading>
    <section>
      <num>21.22</num>
      <heading>Fur-Bearing Animals and Trapping Regulations</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Only tribal members may take fur-bearing animals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Only tribal members may trap.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The season for trapping fur-bearing animals shall be October 20 – April 15.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Quotas for the number of fur-bearing animals that may be trapped during the season shall be set at the beginning of the season based on the recommendation of the Conservation/Ecology Departments and acceptance of the Fish and Wildlife Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Seasonal quotas will be posted at tribal posting places, the Little Star Convenience Store, in the Mohican News and on the tribal website.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Once a seasonal quota has been reached or will be reached imminently for a particular animal, the Conservation/Ecology Departments will close the trapping season for that animal.  Notice of season closure will be posted by the Conservation/Ecology Departments at tribal posting places, the Little Star Convenience Store, in the Mohican News and on the tribal website.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>All traps and fur-bearing animals taken pursuant to these regulations shall have the tribal member's enrollment number clearly marked on them.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>When shipping furs, the parcel must be plainly marked on the outside stating the name, address, permit number of the shipper, the number and kind of skins contained in the package. The bill of lading or receipt issued by any common carrier to a shipper shall specify the number and species of furs shipped.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>Hides or pelts adapted to personal use need not carry the permit number once the adaptation is completion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(G)</num>
        <text>Coyotes may be taken year-round with a with a weapon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(H)</num>
        <text>Bobcat, Badger, Fisher, and Otter:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Trappers must report their trappings with the Conservation/Ecology Departments within 48 hours of the trapping.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A seasonal quota will be set for bobcat, badger, fisher, and otter on an annual basis based on the recommendations of the Conservation/Ecology Departments and acceptance by the Fish and Wildlife Board.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Once the quota has been met, the Conservation/Ecology Departments shall post such notice at the Little Star Convenience Store, the Conservation Department and the Tribe's web site.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Tribal members must obtain a transportation tag from the Ecology Department, if the bobcat, badger, fisher, and/or otter will be transported off of the reservation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>If the hides or pelts legally harvested on tribal lands are to leave the State of Wisconsin, then a CITES tag may also be needed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.23</num>
      <heading>Commercial Trapping</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>The skins/pelts of all fur-bearing animals may be taken to be offered for sale.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.24</num>
      <heading>Trapping Infractions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Class A Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any person who kills, wounds, catches, takes, traps, or has in his/her possession any bird, small game, big game, turkey, or fur-bearing animal included in this Ordinance without a valid permit or permits shall be guilty of a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Taking, assisting in taking, possessing or transporting any game in violation of this Ordinance shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Wanton destruction or waste of any animal on tribal lands shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.  Waste shall include the failure to process an animal in a timely manner.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Violating the terms and/or conditions of any Special Permit shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to use a set gun or swivel gun for any purpose.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to take game with the use of drugs, medicated bait, poison, or other deleterious substances. Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Any person who intentionally disturbs the personal property of another person engaged in lawful activities under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>Any person who molests, takes or appropriates a trap belonging to another person or the animal or contents of a lawfully placed trap belonging to another person shall be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Class B Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Allowing any other person to make use of his/her permit, regardless of whether or not such person would qualify to receive a permit in his/her own right, shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Exceeding established limits, using prohibited means or equipment, using bait contrary to tribal law, hunting outside of established seasons and/or hours shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Fraud in the procurement of any permit shall be deemed a Class B Infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Class C Infractions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Carrying a firearm in any motor vehicle, unless the firearm chamber is unloaded, or a loaded magazine is not attached to the firearm or the firearm is otherwise broken down, shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.  Rounds may be stored separately from the firearm or in a separate magazine, so long as the magazine is not attached to the firearm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Hunting from a snowmobile or chasing game with a snowmobile or other motor vehicle shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Refusal of any person engaged in any activity relating to trapping regulated under this Ordinance to display the proper permit or identification upon request of any Authorized Law Enforcement Personnel shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to take big game or turkey with the aid of any trap or snare.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to deposit any game entrails, body parts, and/or hide, into the waters of any creek, stream, river or lake or to dispose of same within 150 feet of any creek, stream, river, lake, Public Road, residence or residential area.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Any person who uses a vehicle or other means to block a Public Road with the intent of limiting access for other individuals to engage in activities permitted under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class C infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>PART</prefix>
    <num>V</num>
    <heading>OTHER REQUIREMENTS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>21.25</num>
      <heading>Motor Vehicles</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Motor vehicles are prohibited on forest roads during spring break up, except as otherwise authorized under tribal law.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>ATVs, UTVs and snowmobiles are exempt from the spring break-up road closure.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Forest roads are defined under Chapter 22.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Motor vehicles and ATV's are prohibited beyond the dells landing and other posted sensitive areas.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.26</num>
      <heading>Motor Vehicle and Transportation Related Infractions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Class A Infractions</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Transporting any game in violation of this Ordinance shall be deemed a Class A Infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Class B Infractions</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any person who uses a light for wildlife viewing at night after 10 PM or who has a firearm/bow in their vehicle while using a light for wildlife viewing shall be subject to a Class B infraction.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Class C Infractions</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Carrying a firearm in any motor vehicle, unless the firearm chamber is unloaded, or a loaded magazine is not attached to the firearm or the firearm is otherwise broken down, shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.  Rounds may be stored separately from the firearm or in a separate magazine, so long as the magazine is not attached to the firearm.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Hunting from a snowmobile or chasing game with a snowmobile or other motor vehicle shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>It shall be unlawful to discharge any weapon across or down any road, or to hunt within fifty (50) feet of any paved road.  Violation of this provision shall be deemed a Class C Infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Motor vehicles or ATV use in a prohibited area is a Class C infraction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Any person who uses a vehicle or other means to block a road with the intent of limiting access for other individuals to engage in activities permitted under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class C infraction</text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.27</num>
      <heading>Protected Species</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>There shall be no taking, possessing or transporting at any time of species listed as protected, threatened, or endangered under federal law, including, but not limited to, those listed under the Bald and Golden Eagle Protection Act, the Migratory Bird Treaty Act, the Lacey Act, and the Endangered Species Act.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>There shall be no taking, possession, or transporting at any time of any species of fish or wildlife that may from time to time be established or reintroduced into the lands and waters of the Stockbridge-Munsee Community until such time as the Tribal Council deems appropriate by establishing a seasons and regulations pertaining to such species.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The taking of elk, mountain lion, pine marten and moose shall not be permitted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>The taking of a wolf shall not be permitted unless the wolf poses an immediate threat to human safety.  In the event of a taking due to an immediate threat to human safety, the individual shall immediately contact tribal game wardens/conservation officers; the carcass and site shall not be disturbed.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.28</num>
      <heading>Other Infractions</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Aiding, abetting or conspiring with another person to knowingly cause any person to violate any provision of this Ordinance or any rules and regulations adopted hereunder shall be a Class A infraction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Any person who enters or remains on any land owned by the Stockbridge-Munsee Community without the Tribe's authorization shall be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Any other violation or prohibited practice shall be a Class A infraction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Any person who knowingly obstructs Authorized Law Enforcement in fulfilling his or her duties under this Ordinance shall be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <text>Any person who releases a non-native species, except as authorized by Tribal Council or law, shall be subject to a Class A infraction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(F)</num>
        <text>Any tribal member or permittee who abuses his or her privileges, which include the use of motorized vehicles and leaving hunting equipment in place overnight, under this Ordinance to provide assistance to an individual that is not a tribal member or permittee and who is participating in lawful recreation activities on tribal fee lands shall be subject to a Class A infraction.  This provision is not intended to limit a person's ability to provide emergency assistance when there is an individual in need of aid.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>PART</prefix>
    <num>VI</num>
    <heading>- APPLICATION</heading>
    <section>
      <num>21.29</num>
      <heading>Enforcement</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Both Stockbridge-Munsee Law Enforcement Officers and Game Wardens/Conservation Officers are considered "Authorized Law Enforcement" for purposes of enforcement of Chapters 21 and 22 of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Law (hereinafter referred to as "Ordinances" in this <cite path="§21.29">Section 21.29</cite>) and, as such, have authority to investigate and enforce the provisions of such Ordinance.  Authorized Law Enforcement shall consult with other law enforcement agencies, where appropriate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>Authorized Law Enforcement is authorized to investigate and pursue violations of these Ordinances.  This may include observing persons engaged in activities under these Ordinances to ensure that the methods and equipment are lawful.  Authorized Law Enforcement shall conduct such activities in good faith and in accordance with good law enforcement practices and may take such actions as appropriate to the circumstances and under applicable laws.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Authorized Law Enforcement may issue warnings and/or citations to individuals who violate these Ordinances.  Such warnings and/or citations are considered to be civil in nature, rather than criminal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Authorized Law Enforcement have authority to confiscate and seize hunting and/or fishing equipment, weapons, vehicles or any other equipment used in violating these Ordinances.</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>If equipment, vehicles or weapons are confiscated and seized, such equipment, vehicles or weapons shall be considered evidence and properly recorded and secured at the offices of the applicable Authorized Law Enforcement officers pending return or disposition in accordance with tribal law.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>If the alleged violator pays the amount of the citation before the court hearing date, the confiscated equipment, vehicles or weapons (except for illegal items) shall be returned to the ordinance violator unless subject to confiscation under other applicable law.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Authorized Law Enforcement also has authority to confiscate and seize fish and game obtained in violation of these Ordinances.  The confiscated fish or game shall be documented and/or photographed for evidence purposes.  If the fish or game is suitable for human consumption, Authorized Law Enforcement shall turn the fish or game over to the Elderly Department or Tribal elders.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>The citation must be served on the person responsible for the violation in a timely manner with copies delivered to the Tribal Court and Tribal Prosecutor within three (3) business days of service.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Prosecutor shall use his or her discretion to prosecute violations of this Ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Persons convicted of violations to this Ordinance shall be subject to the penalties herein described.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>In addition to forfeiture actions the Tribal Prosecutor may seek enforcement <br/>of any and all parts of this Ordinance by Court actions seeking injunctions or restraining orders.  The Tribal Prosecutor may seek an emergency order from the Court to restrain or enjoin any violation that is jeopardizing the health or safety of any person. Such an order may be sought and issued ex parte if the Tribe shows a good faith effort to serve notice on the necessary parties.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>If the Court finds the person not guilty of the alleged violation, any property or equipment seized by Authorized Law Enforcement shall be returned to the person.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Penalties.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Any person found guilty of this Ordinance shall be assessed of a fine ranging from $100.00 to $5,000 as specified in <cite path="§21.21|(D)|(6)" proof="needed">Section 21.21(D)(6)</cite>, (7) or (8).  In assessing the fine, the Court shall consider the severity of the offense, the acceptance of responsibility by the charged person, the number of previous convictions, and deterrence to others.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>In lieu of or in addition to any other penalty, the Tribal Court may also order that equipment or property seized by Authorized Law Enforcement not be returned to the violator and the equipment or property to become permanent property of the Conservation Department to be used of or disposed of at the Tribal Council's discretion.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>In lieu of or in addition to any other penalty, any person found guilty of    <br/>violating this Ordinance may be required by the Tribal Court to provide community service or such other relief as is necessary and property for the enforcement of this ordinance.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>The Tribal Court may also order suspension of hunting or fishing privileges not to exceed five years.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Revenues received from fines or forfeitures are to be deposited into the Tribe's general revenues.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Civil remedial money penalties, referred to in this Ordinance as Fish &amp; Game Infraction(s) are classified and carry penalties as follows and other remedies as the court deems appropriate:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>Class A Infractions, not less than $500.00 nor more than $5,000.00.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>Class B Infractions, not less than $300.00 nor more than $5,000.00.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>Class C Infractions, not less than $200.00 nor more than $5,000.00.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>When any person is found guilty of a violation, and such person has been convicted of a previous violation of this Ordinance within a period of one year, there shall be a mandatory revocation of all privileges regulated under this Ordinance for a minimum of two years, and the Infraction penalties may be enhanced as follows and other remedies as the court deems appropriate:</text>
          <para>
            <num>(a)</num>
            <text>For a Class A Infraction, $5,000.00.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(b)</num>
            <text>For a Class B Infraction, not less than $1,000.00 nor more than $5,000.00.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>(c)</num>
            <text>For a Class C Infraction, not less than $500.00 nor more than $5,000.00.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(8)</num>
          <text>For a third violation of this Ordinance within a period of one (1) year the penalty shall be $5,000.00 and a mandatory lifetime revocation of all privileges regulated under this Ordinance and other remedies as the court deems appropriate.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(E)</num>
        <heading>Civil Damages.</heading>
        <text>In addition to an action for civil penalties, the Tribe may bring a civil action for recovery of damages against any person unlawfully killing, wounding, catching, taking, trapping, harvesting, or having unlawfully in his or her possession any game animal, fish, or bird.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.30</num>
      <heading>Parties to a Violation</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>Whoever is concerned in the commission of a violation of this Ordinance is a principal and may be charged with the violation although he or she did not directly commit it and although the person who directly committed it has not been convicted of the violation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>A person is concerned in the commission of a violation if the person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Directly commits the violation; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Aids and abets the commission of it; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Is a party to a conspiracy with another to commit it or advises, hires, or counsels or otherwise procures another to commit it.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Any person who attempts any violation of this ordinance shall be subject to the same class of infraction if they had completed all the steps for a violation.  An attempt to commit a violation requires that the actor have an intent to perform acts and attain a result which, if accomplished, would constitute a violation and that the actor does acts towards the commission of the violation which demonstrate unequivocally, under all the circumstances, that the actor formed that intent and would commit the crime except for the intervention of another person or some other extraneous factor.</text>
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.31</num>
      <heading>Tribal Court</heading>
      <text>The Tribal Court shall have jurisdiction over all violations of this Ordinance.  The burden of proof is on the Tribe to prove with clear and convincing evidence that a violation of this Ordinance has occurred.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.32</num>
      <heading>Severability</heading>
      <text>In the event that any provision of this Ordinance is ruled illegal by a court of competent jurisdiction, the remaining provisions of this Ordinance shall remain unaffected.</text>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>21.33</num>
      <heading>Amendments</heading>
      <text>Amendments to this Ordinance will be effective upon enactment by the Stockbridge-Munsee Community Tribal Council without further review by the Secretary of Interior.</text>
    </section>
  </container>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Legislative History">
      <para>
        <num>1</num>
        <heading>Legislative Note:</heading>
        <text>Chapter 20 initially part of Conservation Code, which was adopted by the Tribal Council on November 14, 1978; for additional Legislative History on Conservation Code, see Chapter 22.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2</num>
        <text>Amended by Council motion of Council, July 15, 1997.  New provisions include allowing minor-aged direct descendants to hunt during tribal season, shortening of deer gun season; adding turkey season guidelines; changing brook trout and bass bag limits; prohibiting 4-wheel drive vehicles on logging roads during spring break up; closing road south of Richard's Bridge; mandatory registration; wildlife count.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3</num>
        <text>Amended on March 21, 2000 by Resolution No. 010-2000.  Approval by BIA April 11, 2000.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4</num>
        <text><cite path="§21.9|(A)">Section 21.9(A)</cite> amended creating deer donation policy by Tribal Council on January 2, 2002, Resolution Number 03-02.  Approved by BIA January 15, 2002.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5</num>
        <heading>Legislative Note:</heading>
        <text>The March 21, 2000 amendments regarding fees were not properly incorporated into the Ordinance.  Upon this discovery, the appropriate fees were incorporated into the Ordinance on November 5, 2003, following the November 4, 2003 Tribal Council meeting.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6</num>
        <text>On July 20, 2004, by Resolution No. 039-04, Tribal Council amended sections <cite path="§21.1|(A)">21.1(A)</cite> and (B), <cite path="§21.11|(C)">21.11(C)</cite>, <cite path="§21.13">21.13 </cite>by inserting "and the Stockbridge-Munsee Fish and Game Board;" sections <cite path="§21.2|(A)">21.2(A)</cite> and (B) by deleting requirement to obtain State of Wisconsin licenses; sections <cite path="§21.3|(A)">21.3(A)</cite> and (B) by changing the fees; creating <cite path="§21.3|(C)">section 21.3(C)</cite>;  deleting <cite path="§21.6|(5)" proof="needed">section 21.6(5)</cite>  "Fur bearing animal"; deleting "bald eagle, elk, fisher, golden eagle, marten, timber wolf, lynx or any species determined to be rare or" from <cite path="§21.6|(C)|(4)" proof="needed">section 21.6(C)(4)</cite>; adding "no more than ten grouse" to <cite path="§21.7|(D)">section 21.7(D)</cite>; adding sections <cite path="§21.8|(E)">21.8(E)</cite> and <cite path="§21.10|(E)" proof="needed">21.10(E)</cite>; creating reporting requirement to <cite path="§21.9|(A)|(4)" proof="needed">section 21.9(A)(4)</cite>; amending sections <cite path="§21.9|(A)|(2)" proof="needed">21.9(A)(2)</cite> and <cite path="§21.9|(B)">21.9(B)</cite> to clarify the type and size of weapon or firearm; deleted "the restrictions on the manner for taking bear are the same as outlined in (A)(1) of this section" from <cite path="§21.9|(B)|(1)">section 21.9(B)(1)</cite>; creating <cite path="§21.11|(B)|(1)">section 21.11(B)(1)</cite>; and creating <cite path="§21.14">section 21.14</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>7</num>
        <text>Amended by Tribal Council on June 6, 2006, by creating <cite path="§21.9|(D)">section 21.9(D)</cite>, Resolution No. 044-06.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>8</num>
        <text>Amended by Tribal Council on July 18, 2006, by creating sections <cite path="§21.2|(D)" proof="needed">21.2(D)</cite>, <cite path="§21.3|(A)|(4)" proof="needed">21.3(A)(4)</cite>, <cite path="§21.3|(B)|(3)" proof="needed">21.3(B)(3)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(A)">21.8(A)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(B)|(1)|(2)|(3)" proof="needed">21.8(B)(1)(2)(3)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(C)|(1)|(2)" proof="needed">21.8 (C)(1)(2)</cite>, and <cite path="§21.11|(A)|(1)|(2)|(3)" proof="needed">21.11(A)(1)(2)(3)</cite>; and amending <cite path="§21.3|(A)|(3)" proof="needed">section 21.3(A)(3)</cite>, Resolution No. 051-06.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>9</num>
        <text>Amended by Tribal Council on November 7, 2006, by deleting, "Tribal members may request their harvest tags be mailed to them," from <cite path="§21.11|(A)|(1)" proof="needed">Section 21.11(A)(1)</cite>, Resolution No. 011-07.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>10</num>
        <text>On May 6, 2008, Tribal Council repealed existing Chapter 21 and adopted a new Chapter 21 that renumbered and had changes clarifying numerous sections and incorporated enforcement and other relevant sections of Chapter 20.  This was done by Resolution No. 030-08.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>11</num>
        <text>On October 9, 2008, Tribal Council made an administrative correction by adding the words "or permittee" to <cite path="§21.15">Section 21.15</cite>.5 (C).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>12</num>
        <text>Amendments adopted by Tribal Council on January 6, 2009 to create new Sections <cite path="§21.3|(P)">21.3 (P)</cite>, <cite path="§21.7|(F)">21.7 (F)</cite>, <cite path="§21.10|(D)" proof="needed">21.10 (D)</cite>, <cite path="§21.13|(C)|(1)">21.13 (C)(1)</cite>, <cite path="§21.13|(E)" proof="needed">21.13 (E)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15|(B)|(4)" proof="needed">21.15 (B)(4)</cite>, and <cite path="§21.20|(EE)" proof="needed">21.20 (EE)</cite>; renumber <cite path="§21.10|(D)" proof="needed">Section 21.10 (D)</cite> as <cite path="§21.10|(E)" proof="needed">21.10 (E)</cite>; amend <cite path="§21.16|(A)">Section 21.16 (A)</cite>; move <cite path="§21.15|(A)|(2)" proof="needed">Section 21.15 (A)(2)</cite> to be <cite path="§21.15|(F)" proof="needed">Section 21.15 (F)</cite>; and make a technical change to <cite path="§21.21">Section 21.21</cite>.  On February 3, 2009, Tribal Council renumbered the resolution adopting amendments as Resolution No. 021-09.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>13</num>
        <text>Amendment adopted by Tribal Council on September 1, 2009 to amend Sections <cite path="§21.13">21.13</cite>, <cite path="§21.16|(A)|(3)" proof="needed">21.16 (A)(3)</cite> and <cite path="§21.20|(D)" proof="needed">21.20(D)</cite>; and to create new Sections <cite path="§21.13|(C)|(2)">21.13(C)(2)</cite> and <cite path="§21.13|(C)|(3)">21.13(C)(3)</cite>.  This was done by Resolution No. 082-09.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>14</num>
        <text>On November 16, 2010, the Tribal Council adopted changes to Chapter 21 amending Sections <cite path="§21.8|(C)">21.8(C)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite>.5(C)(1), and <cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite>.5(G) and creating new Sections <cite path="§21.3|(Q)">21.3(Q)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(A)|(1)">21.8(A)(1)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(G)">21.8(G)</cite> and <cite path="§21.20|(FF)" proof="needed">21.20(FF)</cite>.  These changes were adopted by Resolution No. 06-11.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>15</num>
        <text>On June 5, 2012, the Tribal Council adopted the following changes to Chapter 21:</text>
        <text>
          <ul proof="needed">
            <li>Amending <cite path="§21.2|(A)">21.2(A)</cite>, <cite path="§21.4">21.4</cite>, <cite path="§21.15|(B)|(2)" proof="needed">21.15(B)(2)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite>.5(A), <cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite>.5(B), <cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite>.5(C), <cite path="§21.17|(B)">21.17(B)</cite>, <cite path="§21.19|(A)">21.19(A)</cite>, <cite path="§21.20|(V)" proof="needed">21.20(V)</cite>, <cite path="§21.21|(A)">21.21(A)</cite> and <cite path="§21.21|(B)">21.21 (B)</cite>; and</li>
            <li>Deleting <cite path="§21.8|(A)|(1)">21.8(A)(1)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(C)|(1)">21.8(C)(1)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15|(D)">21.15(D)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15|(E)" proof="needed">21.15(E)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite>.5(D)-(G), <cite path="§21.17|(F)|(2)|(d)" proof="needed">21.17(F)(2)(d)</cite>, <cite path="§21.17|(G)|(1)" proof="needed">21.17(G)(1)</cite> and <cite path="§21.21|(B)|(3)|(a)" proof="needed">21.21(B)(3)(a)</cite>-(b); and</li>
            <li>Creating new <cite path="§21.2|(B)">21.2(B)</cite>, <cite path="§21.12|(C)">21.12(C)</cite>, <cite path="§21.12|(D)">21.12(D)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15|(A)|(1)|(c)" proof="needed">21.15(A)(1)(c)</cite>, <cite path="§21.17|(A)|(1)">21.17(A)(1)</cite>-(3), <cite path="§21.20|(GG)" proof="needed">21.20(GG)</cite> and <cite path="§21.21|(B)|(2)|(a)" proof="needed">21.21(B)(2)(a)</cite>-(b); and</li>
            <li>Renumbering <cite path="§21.17|(F)|(2)|(e)" proof="needed">21.17(F)(2)(e)</cite>-(g), <cite path="§21.17|(G)|(2)" proof="needed">21.17(G)(2)</cite>-(4), <cite path="§21.19">21.19 </cite>and <cite path="§21.21">21.21</cite>; and</li>
            <li>Technical change <cite path="§21.6|(B)">21.6(B)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(H)">21.8(H)</cite>, <cite path="§21.17|(C)">21.17(C)</cite> and <cite path="§21.21|(D)|(1)" proof="needed">21.21(D)(1)</cite>.</li>
          </ul>
        </text>
        <text>These changes were adopted by Resolution No. 040-12.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>16</num>
        <text>On October 23, 2012, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 007-13, which authorized changes to Chapter 21 to add requirement that individuals be at least 12-years of age, clarifying the time frame for permits and seasons, and to clarify other language.  These changes are:  amending <cite path="§21.8|(A)">21.8 (A)</cite> to create subsection (1) and a new subsection (2); amending <cite path="§21.8|(B)">21.8 (B)</cite>; amending <cite path="§21.8|(C)">21.8 (C)</cite> to create a new subsection (1) and subsection (2); amending <cite path="§21.8|(H)">21.8 (H)</cite>; amending <cite path="§21.9|(A)|(2)" proof="needed">21.9 (A)(2)</cite> and (3); amending <cite path="§21.9|(B)|(1)">21.9 (B)(1)</cite>, (2) and (3); amending <cite path="§21.16|(A)|(1)">21.16 (A)(1)</cite>; and amending <cite path="§21.21|(B)|(2)|(a)" proof="needed">21.21 (B)(2)(a)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>17</num>
        <text>On November 5, 2013, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 07-14, which authorized changes to Chapter 21 adding a new deer sustenance tag, allowing mentor hunting by 10- and 11-year olds, and clarifying required permits and fees for permittees who are minors. These changes are:  amending sub<cite path="§21.8|(A)|(2)">section 21.8 (A)(2)</cite>; amending sub<cite path="§21.8|(C)|(1)">section 21.8 (C)(1)</cite>; amending sub<cite path="§21.8|(D)">section 21.8 (D)</cite>; adding new sub<cite path="§21.8|(I)">section 21.8 (I)</cite>; adding new subparts <cite path="§21.8|(I)|(1)" proof="needed">21.8 (I)(1)</cite>-(4); adding new sub<cite path="§21.8|(J)" proof="needed">section 21.8 (J)</cite>; adding new subparts <cite path="§21.8|(J)|(1)" proof="needed">21.8 (J)(1)</cite>-(4) and amending sub<cite path="§21.9|(B)|(2)">section 21.9 (B)(2)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>18</num>
        <text>On August 19, 2014, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 043-14, which authorized changes to Chapter 21 to limit baiting and feeding to control the spread of chronic wasting disease, as well as to address using resources responsibly, tagging of equipment, hunting by permittees, turkey harvest and hunting bear with dogs. These changes are to add sections <cite path="§21.12">21.12</cite>.5, <cite path="§21.1|(I)">21.1(I)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(K)" proof="needed">21.8(K)</cite>, <cite path="§21.8|(L)" proof="needed">21.8(L)</cite>, <cite path="§21.15|(C)|(3)">21.15(C)(3)</cite>, and <cite path="§21.15|(D)">21.15(D)</cite>; and to amend sections <cite path="§21.9|(A)|(4)" proof="needed">21.9(A)(4)</cite>, <cite path="§21.14|(B)|(1)">21.14(B)(1)</cite>, <cite path="§21.14|(C)|(1)">21.14(C)(1)</cite>-(3), <cite path="§21.15|(C)">21.15(C)</cite>, and <cite path="§21.20|(E)" proof="needed">21.20(E)</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>19</num>
        <text>On June 3, 2015, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 048-15, which authorized clarifications in relation to turkey hunting fees for permittees, the trout season for tribal members and citations.  These changes amend subsections <cite path="§21.9|(A)|(4)" proof="needed">21.9(A)(4)</cite>, <cite path="§21.9|(B)|(3)">21.9(B)(3)</cite>, <cite path="§21.10|(D)" proof="needed">21.10(D)</cite>, and <cite path="§21.21|(B)|(1)|(b)" proof="needed">21.21 (B)(1)(b)</cite>, (C), (C)(4), (D)(2) and (D)(3).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>20</num>
        <text>On September 6, 2016, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 063-16, which authorized changes to Chapter 21 to rename a fishing pond, clarify use of lead shot, and modify hunting seasons.  The changes amend subsections <cite path="§21.10|(E)" proof="needed">21.10(E)</cite>, <cite path="§21.12">21.12</cite>.5(C), <cite path="§21.13|(C)|(1)">21.13(C)(1)</cite>, <cite path="§21.14|(B)|(2)">21.14(B)(2)</cite> and <cite path="§21.15|(A)">21.15(A)</cite> and create new subsections <cite path="§21.13|(E)" proof="needed">21.13(E)</cite> (1) and (2).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>21</num>
        <text>On August 15, 2017, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 042-17, which authorized changes to Chapter 21 to:  redefine big game to not include turkey; define adult bear and cub; retitle department names; increase age for permittee fishing to 16; eliminate fees for minor-age direct descendants to hunt and fish; and eliminate the buck-only season.  These changes:</text>
        <text>
          <ul proof="needed">
            <li>Amend sections:  <cite path="§21.3|(A)">21.3(A)</cite>,(C) and (J); <cite path="§21.5|(B)|(5)">21.5(B)(5)</cite>; <cite path="§21.6|(A)">21.6(A)</cite>,(C) and (D); <cite path="§21.7|(A)">21.7(A)</cite>; <cite path="§21.8|(D)">21.8(D)</cite> and (H); <cite path="§21.9|(B)">21.9(B)</cite>; <cite path="§21.14|(A)">21.14 (A)</cite>; <cite path="§21.15|(A)">21.15(A)</cite> and(C); <cite path="§21.16|(A)">21.16(A)</cite>, (B) and (C); <cite path="§21.17|(A)|(3)">21.17(A)(3)</cite>, (F)(7) and (G); <cite path="§21.18|(A)">21.18(A)</cite>; and <cite path="§21.20|(A)">21.20 (A)</cite>, (Q).</li>
            <li>Create the following new sections: <cite path="§21.3|(R)">21.3(R)</cite> and (S); and <cite path="§21.15|(C)|(2)">21.15(C)(2)</cite>.</li>
            <li>Delete the following sections:  <cite path="§21.9|(B)|(1-3)" proof="needed">21.9(B)(1-3)</cite>; and <cite path="§21.15|(B)|(4)" proof="needed">21.15 (B)(4)</cite>.</li>
          </ul>
        </text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>22</num>
        <text>On September 3, 2019, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 069-19, which re-organized content to make it more convenient for readers by grouping similar provisions into parts and re-arranging and re-numbering accordingly.  Additionally, substantive changes to modify bag limits for deer, turkey, and trout were made and clarifications about roads where hunting is limited and assistance to other persons were made.  More specifically, the following changes were made.</text>
        <text>
          <ul proof="needed">
            <li>Moved:</li>
          </ul>
        </text>
        <para>
          <num>
            <cite path="§21.8|(B)">21.8 (B)</cite>
          </num>
          <text>to <cite path="§21.9|(A)">21.9 (A)</cite></text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>
            <cite path="§21.8|(J)" proof="needed">21.8 (J)</cite>
          </num>
          <text>to <cite path="§21.8|(C)">21.8 (C)</cite></text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>
            <cite path="§21.8|(K)" proof="needed">21.8 (K)</cite>
          </num>
          <text>to <cite path="§21.8|(D)">21.8 (D)</cite></text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>
            <cite path="§21.8|(L)" proof="needed">21.8 (L)</cite>
          </num>
          <text>to <cite path="§21.8|(E)">21.8 (E)</cite></text>
          <text>
            <ul proof="needed">
              <li><cite path="§21.10">21.10 </cite>to <cite path="§21.19">21.19</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.11">21.11 </cite>to <cite path="§21.20">21.20</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.12">21.12 </cite>to <cite path="§21.27">21.27</cite></li>
            </ul>
          </text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>
            <cite path="§21.15|(A)">21.15 (A)</cite>
          </num>
          <text>and (B) to <cite path="§21.10">21.10 </cite>with (A) separated into (A) and (B)</text>
          <text>
            <ul proof="needed">
              <li><cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite>.5 to <cite path="§21.11">21.11</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.12">21.12</cite>.5 to <cite path="§21.12">21.12</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.13">21.13 </cite>to <cite path="§21.15">21.15</cite></li>
            </ul>
          </text>
        </para>
        <aftertext>
          <ul proof="needed">
            <li>New <cite path="§21.13">21.13 </cite>moved final sentence of (B) to be new (A)</li>
          </ul>
        </aftertext>
        <para>
          <num>
            <cite path="§21.15|(E)" proof="needed">21.15 (E)</cite>
          </num>
          <text>to <cite path="§21.12|(D)">21.12 (D)</cite></text>
          <text>
            <ul proof="needed">
              <li><cite path="§21.16">21.16 </cite>to <cite path="§21.18">21.18</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.17">21.17 </cite>to <cite path="§21.22">21.22</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.18">21.18 </cite>to <cite path="§21.16|(portion on hunting)" proof="needed">21.16 (portion on hunting)</cite> and <cite path="§21.23|(portion on trapping)" proof="needed">21.23 (portion on trapping)</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.19">21.19 </cite>to <cite path="§21.25">21.25</cite></li>
              <li><cite path="§21.20">21.20 </cite>to <cite path="§21.17|(on hunting)" proof="needed">21.17 (on hunting)</cite>, <cite path="§21.21|(on fishing)" proof="needed">21.21 (on fishing)</cite>, <cite path="§21.24|(on trapping)" proof="needed">21.24 (on trapping)</cite>, <cite path="§21.26|(on vehicles)" proof="needed">21.26 (on vehicles)</cite>, and <cite path="§21.28">21.28</cite></li>
              <li>Starting from previous <cite path="§21.21">21.21 </cite>the sections were renumbered beginning at <cite path="§21.29">21.29</cite></li>
              <li>Amended sections:  <cite path="§21.1|(G)">21.1 (G)</cite>; <cite path="§21.3|(C)">21.3 (C)</cite>, (H); <cite path="§21.6|(B)">21.6 (B)</cite>; <cite path="§21.8|(A)">21.8 (A)</cite>, (F), (G); <cite path="§21.9|(B)">21.9 (B)</cite>, (B)(1-3); <cite path="§21.10|(B)">21.10 (B)</cite>; <cite path="§21.14|(B)|(1)">21.14 (B)(1)</cite> and (C)(1); <cite path="§21.15|(C)">21.15 (C)</cite>; <cite path="§21.18|(A)|(4)">21.18 (A)(4)</cite>; <cite path="§21.19|(C)">21.19 (C)</cite>; <cite path="§21.22|(C)|(1)">21.22 (C)(1)</cite>, (E), (H)(4); <cite path="§21.23|(A)">21.23 (A)</cite>; and <cite path="§21.25|(A)">21.25 (A)</cite>, (A)(1-2).</li>
              <li>Created new sections:  <cite path="§21.3|(T)">21.3 (T)</cite>; <cite path="§21.8|(A)|(3)">21.8 (A)(3)</cite>; <cite path="§21.9|(D)">21.9 (D)</cite> and (E); <cite path="§21.17">21.17</cite>; <cite path="§21.19|(A)">21.19 (A)</cite> (this is based on <cite path="§21.9|(A)">21.9 (A)</cite>); <cite path="§21.21">21.21</cite>; <cite path="§21.22|(A)">21.22 (A)</cite> and (B), (H)(2), (H)(5), (G); <cite path="§21.24">21.24</cite>; <cite path="§21.26">21.26</cite>; and <cite path="§21.28|(F)">21.28 (F)</cite>.</li>
              <li>Deleted section (numbering from previous): <cite path="§21.8|(D)">21.8 (D)</cite>; <cite path="§21.8|(I)">21.8 (I)</cite>; <cite path="§21.9|(A)|(2)" proof="needed">21.9 (A)(2)</cite>; <cite path="§21.13|(E)" proof="needed">21.13 (E)</cite>; and <cite path="§21.17|(F)" proof="needed">21.17 (F)</cite>.</li>
            </ul>
          </text>
        </para>
      </para>
    </annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
