<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code">
  <prefix>CHAPTER</prefix>
  <num>45</num>
  <heading>EDUCATION</heading>
  <section>
    <num>45.1</num>
    <heading>Education Board</heading>
    <para>
      <num>(A)</num>
      <text>The Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Education Board, hereinafter called the Education Board, shall consist of 10 members.</text>
    </para>
    <para>
      <num>(B)</num>
      <text>The composition of the Board shall be:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>5 enrolled Stockbridge-Munsee members who are parents or grandparents of Indian children enrolled in either the Bowler or Gresham school systems at the time of their election;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>1 member-at-large (enrolled or non-enrolled) who resides within the Stockbridge-Munsee service area;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>2 enrolled Stockbridge-Munsee secondary students (1 from the Bowler school system and 1 from the Gresham school systems); and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>2 teachers of Indian students (1 from the Bowler school system and 1 Gresham school system).</text>
      </para>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.2</num>
    <heading>Terms</heading>
    <text>The initial membership of the Education Board shall be by appointment by the Tribal Council.  The initial Board shall serve until the next regular annual tribal election, at which time the 5 parents or grandparents of Indian children, and the 1 member at-large shall be elected by popular vote. The 2 secondary students and the 2 teachers shall continue to be appointed by Council on an annual basis, and this appointment shall be made on recommendation of the elected Education Board.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.3</num>
    <heading>Elections</heading>
    <text>At the first election of the 5 enrolled Stockbridge-Munsee parents or enrolled Stockbridge-Munsee grandparents and the 1 member at-large, the 2 persons who receive the highest number of votes shall serve 3 years, the 2 persons who receive the next highest number of votes shall serve 2 years, and the 2 persons who receive the lowest number of votes shall serve 1 year. Thereafter, at each annual election there shall be two terms open to be filled for three year terms, so that an elected members of the Board shall serve three year terms on a staggered basis.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.4</num>
    <heading>Removal</heading>
    <text>The Tribal Council may remove any member of the Education Board by majority vote for neglect of duty or gross misconduct, provided that the member sought to be removed shall be given an opportunity to be heard at a designated council meeting.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.5</num>
    <heading>Power to Appoint</heading>
    <text>Any vacancies which occur on the Education Board shall be filled by appointment by the Tribal Council for the period of the unexpired term.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.6</num>
    <heading>By-laws</heading>
    <text>The initially appointed Education Board shall be responsible for drawing up Bylaws to govern the Education Board, and shall submit these Bylaws to the Tribal Council for final approval within 60 days of their appointment.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.7</num>
    <heading>Purpose</heading>
    <text>The Education Board shall be formed for the purpose of facilitating maximum education services and maximum utilization of available resources for the people of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribe, and shall be responsible to the Tribal Council for making recommendations for priorities, program development and planning, and for the general coordination of an education programs within the Stockbridge-Munsee Community.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.8</num>
    <heading>Duties</heading>
    <text>The Education Board shall perform all such duties as are required to effectively carry out the goals and objectives of the federal Johnson O'Malley, Title IV and Head Start programs, and any other future educational programs which the Tribe may participate in.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.9</num>
    <heading>Advisory Capacity</heading>
    <text>The Education Board shall act as an advisory board to the Head Start Parent Advisory Committee and shall be a liaison between the Head Start Parent Advisory Committee and the Tribal Council.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.10</num>
    <heading>Monthly Minutes to Tribal Council</heading>
    <text>It shall be the duty of the Education Board to submit regular monthly meeting minutes to the Tribal Council for its review.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.11</num>
    <heading>Exclusivity</heading>
    <text>Enactment of this ordinance centralizes responsibility and concern for tribal education matters in the Tribal Education Board, and removes such responsibility from all other existing tribal education committees.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.12</num>
    <heading>Tribal Council Retains Authority</heading>
    <text>This ordinance delegates authority and responsibilities to the Education Board without any concurrent loss of ultimate tribal authority, the tribal education board shall function as an official arm of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council on all education related matters and shall carry out the mandates of the Tribal Council with regard to education.</text>
  </section>
  <section>
    <num>45.13</num>
    <heading>Amendment</heading>
    <text>This ordinance shall be subject to amendment or the addition of further provisions by resolutions of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council.</text>
  </section>
  <annotations>
    <annotation type="Legislative History">
      <text/>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Education ordinance adopted by Tribal Council per resolution no. 0689 dated February 19, 1980. Approved by BIA November 12, 1980.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Ordinance amended by resolution no. 1179 dated February 13, 1990 which created changes in Sections 1 and 10, changes incorporated.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Amended by Tribal Council on October 1, 1996, Resolution No. 078-96 inserting "grandparents" in Sections 45.1, 45.2, and 45.3.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>On October 2, 2012, the Tribal Council adopted Resolution No. 0004-13 amending Sections 45.1, 45.2, 45.8 and 45.9 of the ordinance.</text>
      </para>
    </annotation>
  </annotations>
</container>
