<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council Res. No. 011-20">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective/>
    <history>
      <adopted/>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council Res. No. 011-20</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Stockbridge-Munsee Community is a federally recognized Indian tribe with inherent sovereign powers and is governed by the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council pursuant to the 1937 Constitution, as amended;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council has the authority under its Constitution and its inherent rights as a sovereign nation to adopt and amend Ordinances;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Tribal Council established general rules of civil procedure for its court system under Chapter 5, Civil Procedure, in tribal law;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Tribal Council wishes to now establish a separate ordinance addressing procedure before the Stockbridge-Munsee Court of Appeals; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The present Chapter 5 needs to be modified in order to replace references to appellate procedure with cross reference to the new Chapter 5-A, Appellate Procedure ordinance and deleting language addressing appellate procedure.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council hereby approves changes to Chapter 5 that amend Section 5.2 (A)(3) to add a cross-reference to Chapter 5-A and delete Section 5.22, which previously addressed appellate procedure.</text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council, hereby certify that the Council is composed of 7 members, of whom ____, constituting a quorum, were present at a meeting duly called, noticed, and held on the ____ day of _______, 2019, that the foregoing resolution was duly adopted at such meeting by a vote of ____ for, ____against, and ____abstaining.</text>
    <text>_____________________________				________________________</text>
    <text>Shannon Holsey, President					Jerilyn Johnson, Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
