<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://code.dccouncil.us/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council Res. No. 031-20">
  <heading/>
  <meta>
    <effective/>
    <history>
      <adopted/>
    </history>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council Res. No. 031-20</citation>
    </citations>
  </meta>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Stockbridge-Munsee Community is a federally recognized Indian tribe with inherent sovereign powers and is governed by the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council pursuant to the 1937 Constitution, as amended;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council has the authority under its Constitution and its inherent rights as a sovereign nation to adopt and amend ordinances;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Tribal Council has adopted an Employee Preference Policy Ordinance, Chapter 54, to maximize employment opportunities and benefits to the tribal community;</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>While federal law permits tribal member preference, federal law also requires the Tribe to provide preference to other Indians for federally funded positions; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>The Tribe wishes to amend Chapter 54 in order to identify the order of preference that applies when there is federal funding and make other updates and clarifications to the ordinance.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED,</conjunction>
      <text>that the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council adopts the following amendments to Chapter 54:</text>
    <text>
      <ul proof="needed">
        <li>Numbered the previously unnumbered Purpose section as <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.05" proof="needed">54.05</cite>.  Amended <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.05" proof="needed">54.05 </cite>to update purpose language in (A), add footnote referencing federal law, and add new (B) on Authority.</li>
        <li>Amended <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.1|(B)" proof="needed">54.1 (B)</cite> to delete reference to Mohican Housing Authority since it is now a division of the Tribe.</li>
        <li>Amended <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.1|(C)" proof="needed">54.1 (C)</cite> and (D) and <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.2|(A)" proof="needed">54.2 (A)</cite> to clarify that preference applies when meet minimum qualifications.</li>
        <li>Amended <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.1|(E)" proof="needed">54.1 (E)</cite>, (F), and (G) to correct Tribe's name.</li>
        <li>Added new <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.1|(I)" proof="needed">54.1 (I)</cite>, (J), and (K) to add definitions for Tribe, Other Indians, and Federal Funding.</li>
        <li>Reorganized <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.2|(A)" proof="needed">54.2 (A)</cite> to have subsections.</li>
        <li>Amended <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.3" proof="needed">54.3 </cite>to add new (A); renumber prior (A) as subsection (B) and create an exception for federally funded positions; and to add new (C) for the order of preference for federally funded positions.</li>
        <li>Amended <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.5|(A)" proof="needed">54.5 (A)</cite> and (B) to clarify intent and integrate the Comment, which was deleted.</li>
        <li>Amended remedies under <cite doc="Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Code" path="54.8|(B)" proof="needed">54.8 (B)</cite> to be internally consistent that preference applies in relation to hiring and layoffs.</li>
      </ul>
    </text>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>I, the undersigned, as Secretary of the Stockbridge-Munsee Tribal Council, hereby certify that the Council is composed of 7 members, of whom ____, constituting a quorum, were present at a meeting duly called, noticed, and held on the ____ day of _________, 2020, that the foregoing resolution was duly adopted at such meeting by a vote of ____ for, ____against, and ____abstaining.</text>
    <text>____________________________				________________________</text>
    <text>Shannon Holsey, President					Jerilyn Johnson, Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
</document>
